oh yeah this is Bonnie and Andrew
Venezia we're going to have a nice
conversation here about we spaced
practice and I just wanted to
congratulate Andrew because he's a new
husband and and and father and a and
congratulations on your thesis so I was
thinking about that down at the bars at
Varna the trifecta yeah and I really
want to thank you for doing this
conversation with me because you know I
wanted you to be at the symposium I
thought that that that was a very
important piece or space to be held
there and I know that that it is that
wasn't really working for you but I'm
sure that we can meet up in real
embodied space soon hopefully this is a
this is a long game yeah it's a very
very long game we get to play for we get
to play for a long time absolutely we
had spoken a little earlier just before
we started and I was hoping that we
could create for anyone that is watching
the recording some kind of taste or
quality of the intimacy or the kind of
engagement that constitutes some of this
work constitutes we space it may or may
not be perfectly translatable over the
internet and certainly in recording but
we we talked about working beginning
that way and just kind of orienting
ourselves less toward just a
conversation in a regular interview and
so for me there's a certain process that
that happens when I orient myself that
way and I thought maybe we could start
by sharing what that process feels like
or how do
you interpret that process so
as I start to really feel into engaging
with you one of the first things that
happens is that I like my body and my
you know all of the little bits and
pieces that make up my experience of my
body really relax and start to let go
and I feel like all of the the things
that come in between you and I are just
not present and I'm open and available
to you and it's and it's a very it's
it's beautiful and it's and it's and
it's humbling and it's and it's not like
honor honor full like I'm honored to
come into contact with you and even
though I'm sitting in Belgium you know
and I'm looking at you through a
computer screen I'm very much you know
we're very much here together and
there's something that's so nourishing
and and breathtaking about that and that
never you know I mean I knew that we
were gonna do this all for awhile and
yet it's it's surprising to me every
time it's surprising to me and every
time even if I'm doing it with the same
person there's there's a new feeling
about it so I'm I'm very aware right now
just of that delight and that joy and
and the expanse of it and the and the
presence of it just the very clear and
simple being here with you that's really
again just obvious that's that's what's
going on in my my style yeah that was
really nice
so for me there the this the presence
itself can be overwhelming because like
you're saying it's always a surprise and
it always comes with so much you know
there's so much fullness and so that's
always for me the first process and I
need to work in some sense uphill is a
funny word because I just want to be
with that miss yeah and integrating that
with a conversation we're going to
become intellectual is is is fun because
it's a challenge right so we sit in that
space that fullness and you don't want
to lose it but for me it's about trust
right so for me way down there and this
is what I noticed when we first met and
we don't really know each other very
well but there is this automatic trust
and that then somehow is the fullness of
being with you in the presence so I keep
going like that because it actually
feels like something you know and and
then for me also I that's like a deeper
level and then and then the next level
for me is to work make sure that there
aren't contractions so this would be
more like a subtle level and look where
the energy is and when the energy isn't
and that's not so much happening here
because on one on when the intimacy is
easier yeah and then try to let all of
that
become this becomes discourse which is
hard it's like for me that the effort in
it is like making sure you know it's a
weird way to say it making sure is a
weird way to say it but it's like
relaxing into allowing that that that
fullness to express itself without the
with without the contraction sort of
getting in the way so that's done so the
sense that I have is also you know
there's this really this very
ejaculatory experience of creativity
that's you know popping and popping and
napping most a moment and yet you know
the the that creativity is coming out of
my my effort now I don't I don't think
this is the same for everybody but it
you know very very fine moments a moment
with what I feel like I'm doing right
now my effort is actually being expended
expanded in a significant way on like
holding everything else off like making
sure that everything else is cool like
like a cat herder or something you know
and and then and then it just happens
and that's and that's a very I don't
know that's the that's that's yeah it
just makes me feel very happy like but
it is that that movement is such a you
know there is this wow yeah yeah yeah it
was funny because doing these
conversations with Zak's Schlosser and
you know he just said we space work is
fun cuz it's so much fun you know and so
so of course it's not always fun but
when it's fun it's real real fun and I
think there's a synergy you know one of
the things we discovered about ourselves
is that there's a synergy in the sense
that we open up pretty easy
there's for me not a lot of contraction
that I feel and the technology for me is
a little more of a contraction and then
and then our intellectual play is very a
very nice field and that also can be
rare so we'll get into that but I can
feel my mind saying I want to play I
want to play now and I think when people
it's been my experience that people who
aren't so excited about ideas can see an
interaction that we might have as merely
intellectual and it certainly does not
feel that way you know so and and that's
something special I think that this
particular dyad has especially in terms
of excitement in an intellectual way and
yet and this is maybe not as apparent I
think over like the video right but if
you were here with me present you would
actually see that it's not it's you know
there's there's a it's like a pyramid
you know it's my body is totally in it
it's totally here
yeah harvest for we and if it's over
here I am I'm present emotionally right
now in such a you know this this open
joyful sense and then and then it comes
out of that idea and I think for me you
know obviously so here you and I this is
a very interesting this is a very
interesting space that we're bringing
about now because it is you know
fundamentally it has to be between you
and I at this moment and yet we're also
sort of aware that we're also talking
for an audience
and that makes it very different I think
and so in in a you know an other what
what has what has taken me time to learn
I think is that if I'm in a we space
with someone else who doesn't resonate
in the same way intellectually that I do
then that's okay
that's totally cool and my presence with
them as I'm feeling into what they're
doing and being moment moment will show
up appropriately and it doesn't mean
that my intellect is on the side or
anything but the play aspect of it is
maybe more thoroughly felt in my body or
just you know be in the back and forth
that happens in relationship and being
reality of that there's an ineffable joy
in itself and it just because you and I
happen to love ideas I think it gets
expressed in that way but it's also it's
here and every house - you're in my
hands you know it's here in your clients
oh no the ideas one of the experiences
I've had which is a recent nice
experience a surprise you know this kind
of work comes up with a lot of surprises
is that that when you have the trust and
you have this other thing you were
talking about that joy in the enthusiasm
that people can participate in the
discussion that the the signifier is the
actual shared conversation in multiple
ways and so for example we've had these
experiences on the magellan courses and
with that group where people are invited
to just listen to the play and then the
words bring out poetry or riffs in them
and I you know a real intellectual would
get annoyed because they'd be like you
know we're working here or you are
making just important distinction
serious yes right but if you can allow
this other community presence to arise
it not only gives relief but it creates
in
site right so there's something about
the other aspects of the joy that
creates more possibility for insight
that can come out either as poetry or a
shift in a view with you're an
intellectual so yeah so that it's like I
guess it's also I mean I don't mean this
in a derogatory way but it's like having
children around so you might be working
on your thesis and looking over and
watching children and they're saying
something and it's directly insights
your work because it's a relief you know
it's it's it's it's part of the whole
without being eaten up by your yeah
focus or something like one of the
things I think
wonderful about this but also very
challenging for people is that
everything is included and if there you
know there's a there is a space for
everything which doesn't mean that it's
there it's not a practice of discernment
it's a very strong practice of
discernment book interpersonally you
know in my own self where is this coming
from is this coming from a place where
you know do I want you I want you to see
me in a certain way do I want you to see
me as a smart person right now and if I
do then I'm going to be doing things
that I think you will think you know
blah blah blah if I just let it go like
yeah it doesn't really matter right
that's an intra you know an
interpersonal discernment but there's
there's there's a interpersonal
discernment too and yet it's such a
practice of opening to that to that
fullness and to be able to be affected
by everything here like I'm my spy light
and and you know the world is turning
outside there's a clear clouds and clear
blue sky and that just affected me in a
way that has affected our conversation
now in a positive way in a very
beautiful way that yeah I think the the
difference between you know again and a
lot of what my thesis is about is this
is this shift from making meaning as an
individual in a way that you know where
you're cutting the world up into pieces
right the categorize it and versus
making meaning in a way that in a way
that you know sees that those pieces are
not really fundamentally or the act of
cutting is not something that creates
the pieces as being fundamentally
different from each other I think I just
did a terrible job of explaining that
but and and that you know when you I
totally just froze out of brain freeze I
think you know you know what I mean
though I mean I know what came up for me
no I think I don't know what you mean
yet so I want to go there cuz that's
like where the energy is for you
me so I think that what I heard what
came up in my mind was discernment is
not the same as judgment right and and
judgment is sometimes I think too strong
of a turn because there's also very very
very subtle forms of judgment right so
you could be making discernment and it's
like that joke right what is that joke
the Dalai Lama says you know just go one
day without have any bad thoughts about
someone and the guy goes out man that's
easy to do right there's a subtle
there's a you know so so and I find when
you watch the mind making discernments
it's very very tricky right it's very
tricky and for me watching and yeah it's
very tricky and yet it seems to come in
just a handful of common patterns you
know so that gives us hope to be able to
look at them yeah and so one common
pattern is to make a discernment that
has a subtle or not so subtle boundary
that makes an eye in it or an eye me in
a you or you know I don't want to say I
thou because that term is is about that
that that boundary is not there one you
know
there's always so much going on that
that making those kinds of discernment
and watching that itself is very
interested is what I heard you say
something like that like the cut when
you said the cut is not necessarily a
bad thing or something right well yeah
that's interesting we use the word bad
there because I think that's also one of
the you know one of the sort of
unacknowledged you know when you're
making a judgement you're saying this
one thing here is good and this one
thing here is bad and the practice is I
think or a large part of the practice is
accepting everything as it arises which
you know in your own practice is hard
enough to do I mean if you're sitting on
a meadow and on a meditation cushion
it's really hard to let every single
thing that arise be totally okay but
when you're sitting with another person
and you're trying to do something
together letting every single thing that
arises be okay is infinitely more
difficult and it's infinitely more
difficult for every single person that
you add into that group that's why you
know you said it's it's a little easier
cuz you and I are at that I adhere and
that's very true like the dynamics that
are happened with happening between the
two of us are complex but they're
infinitely less complex and if there
were a third person here and we were
trying to genuinely have a generative
conversation with three people that's
that's that's much tough and it has to
do with you know that that that judgment
comes along with a very subtle but
fundamental rejection of something it's
saying I don't want this right now
and the move is rather to say okay
here's everything here it is right and
and then to make a discernment is to say
not that I don't want this right now but
that this might not have been you know
this might not have been the most
skillful thing to do with the most
skillful thing to say or even to say you
know this is the direction that I think
that I want to go into that I think we
should go into to be able to do that
without in some way making a subtle
judgment of somebody's you know
somebody's being which is you know I
think at a very at a very low
very uh you know basic level is what
we're doing when I say you know don't do
that I'm really saying you know in this
moment you're you're you're wrong right
in this man and you've done something
which which is which is you know which
is impossible it's it's all these
beautiful you know beautiful like
seaweed you know waving in the ocean the
sea me doesn't wave in the wrong way and
it just happens to be that we're seaweed
that thinks that the way the sea and
then a certain way of course that's true
like I I you know it's it's it's
certainly not a practice of everything
being okay regardless like you're not
gonna I'm not gonna practice non
discernment with somebody who walks up
to me in an alley with a knife it's a
very different circumstance but in terms
of lease spaces and that's why that's
also why it's important to have
important to have that interpersonal
discernment because it's much more
difficult back this this with people who
are not at least in some way able to
make the make make the having the
observation to make the insight that how
I'm showing luck right now at this
moment is in some way conditioned by
something that I don't want to be true
yeah
and I think that that I love that
there's no way for a seaweed can wave
the wrong way so we get a bunch of
people together and the relational
dynamics get magnified exponential it's
nonlinear like three is not a third more
than two it's like a lot more than two
and then on and on right and we're not
even counting the background noise I
mean most of this is done in an
experimental setup but if it's done in
the supermarket or you know in the
middle of New York City there's there's
all that too and then so now then you
use the word that I move I could carry
forward in the thing
like I look at it in terms of like that
so we talked about the subtractive thing
you want to subtract the judgment you
want to subtract the conditioned
responses subtract the triggers and it's
it's this is very tricky to talk about I
thing because because it because yes in
a certain sense yes that's true and then
in another sense you know if a judgment
comes up that's also just what's
happened that's another movement yeah so
that's that in itself is okay but you
surface that you make it transparent you
recognize that that has happened and you
say oh you know what's happening right
now I'm judging you for just having said
that but that's interesting
yeah that becomes another thing to make
a judgment on but that becomes a point
of inquiry it becomes a point of a
possible exploration it may not be the
right one at the moment
but it becomes a point of possible its
exploration at the moment so it's
different than saying we don't want to
judgement judgement is bad because
that's just doing the same thing again
that's not that's not the you know
that's the that's the that's a very
mental move that is exactly and and so
that's what you just described is what I
mean by subtraction it's you're
subtracting a certain pattern around
what rises so could be judge you know
and that's exactly the move you make
something comes up it's judgement you
report you don't replace the judgment
you replace the judging the person with
the curious little person no so now I'm
curious Wow look in there it's cool you
know so that's what I that's a little
metaphor that I that I use so but then
there's the additive like you said
something about now we have all these
relational dynamics and and I want to
get back to that because on in another
way I think the relational dynamics
themselves there's like a genius into
the fact that they get very that do they
magnify really quickly I mean I think a
certain level of this work when you come
out the other side my hypothesis is is
that we find that
what looks to us now as obstacles is
actually energy you know that relational
dynamics magnify is a great potential
that they magnify and then get entrained
in these patterns that the energy can't
fit in that is I think where we're at
now so that they magnify is really cool
and it's the same with but I'm going to
so now we're going to add because we're
greedy we're going to add not only do we
want to be able to surf the relational
dynamics but for me the word collective
insight and maybe then we can talk about
your thesis because you it was the first
time I've seen someone say some of these
things like this and I have to admit I
feel that it's a great greedy position
so now we're not only going to be able
to surf these complex relational
dynamics but we're going to say we want
to put this in service to something
right so I call it - in insight so we
might all want to have an insight about
something or you know create a new
imaginary it doesn't have to solve a
problem and and for me at this level
solving problems there really when you
get on the other side they dissolve they
don't really solve yes oh so maybe you
could talk about that and whether or not
you were interested of that in your
thesis or not
you
so you know I'm just I'm wondering and I
think one of the interesting things so
my response to that question of like how
have we done in that so I have like sort
of two they're two points that come up
for me one is that I think somebody
watching this probably unless they're
really tuned in with us it were or I
won't say it that way but it could very
easily look like you and I are just
having a normal conversation between two
people who happen to know each other a
little bit under friend they're sort of
poking at each other in an interpersonal
way slightly and yet for me I'm very
aware of I'm very aware of interacting
with you in this in this in this way but
the focus of our topic has still been we
space practices and not what's going on
between the two of us right so that
makes it so there's there's a lot of
interesting things going on here so I
feel very much in this relational space
with you but we're not putting attention
on that relational space as it exists
between the two of us which makes it a
little bit different and yet that has
been a very you know it's been a strong
experience for me as I'm here with you
I'm I am very conscious of being with
you right now and have been the whole
time that we've been talking and yet I
think from the outside of that probably
you know it's easy for it not to look
that way and I think that that that
speaks to you know these are
participatory spaces you you you you
really need to be and of course I could
totally be projecting that on people ya
know you know what you're thinking if
you're watching us because I'm not doing
that but as I see as a human to that
it's it brings up that sense that you
know you have to you have to engage with
it you can you can you can also study it
but engage with it right you better
actually be doing it yeah a relation
there's a moment-to-moment yeah I feel
the same way I mean the word that came
up for me is I feel I felt and feel a
company company company accompanied you
like like through all of that and and
really it's kind of like the way we set
off and having that feeling of fullness
and then it just it's just like watching
it show up through this and and and I
think that's an important aspect of the
work because we practice the work itself
as an object to create capacity but then
it because it becomes tacit knowledge it
it it you you play in that capacity
that's how I feel with you you know and
and and like we started off by saying
the first time we met each other this
kind of natural synergy you make it easy
you know so but yeah not to get hung up
on what it looks like what I want to
stop you for a second and actually
what's because I that's um I was very
affected by that when you just said that
that was really I thought I felt very
touched by that and I am you just that
that totally lit me up and appreciated
be I appreciate that
what happened was when I was talking
about that I went back to that first I
could see us on the porch there and I
could feel that's you and that I could
feel you you know and I can feel what
that was like
like yeah so and then that's what came
out of my mouth feel you make it easy
cuz that was what I was yeah I went
there and you seemed you know you were
right there and like so so thank you
this has been you know we could have
gone on for who knows when it actually
if we were together like you know you
never know women oh yeah it's a lot in
it's a long game yeah thank you very
much I mean yeah thank you for I mean I
just feel I know I actually have felt
very supported in you know putting my
thesis out there because you've sort of
been there with it like literally every
step of the way like anything you're
almost invariably the first person that
notices and that reads it and that looks
at and then starts to and you know I
think I I definitely you know I have an
audience in writing my paper and that
audience is proposed of a lot of
different people of course but
definitely you were clearly one of the
people that was sitting there as I was
writing a paper and sort of influencing
and going along with it so I'm really
you know I'm both and no I'm just
grateful actually an yeah all right well
you like great evening I guess it's late
there but it's I got to start cooking
dinner for my family actually also got
to start eating dinner but yeah thank
you and I hope you know i hope that this
I hope that this I hope that this is
helpful that it is and it gives people
an idea of what is going on and what
some of the exciting and emerging things
are that are happening and yeah yeah
okay it's the symposium as well I hope
that it helps you know get the word out
about the symposium yes sir we'll talk
again if not before I certainly will
touch base and what the symposium was
like yes for sure Dublin love to your
family yeah thank you
you